<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The royal joy. Or, A sermon of congratulation upon the five first verses of Psalm XXI. Made upon the occasion of the first news of the proclamation of Charls II. King of Great Britain; brought to His Majesty in the town of Breda, the 21. of May, in the year 1660. Preached at the Walloon Church of the said town, the 23. of May, the day before His Majesties departure: by Anthony Hulsius, pastor of the said Church.</title>
            <author>Hulsius, Antonius, 1615-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86711</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3363</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1048_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208129</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867117</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867117</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119407</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86711)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119407)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 155:E1048[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The royal joy. Or, A sermon of congratulation upon the five first verses of Psalm XXI. Made upon the occasion of the first news of the proclamation of Charls II. King of Great Britain; brought to His Majesty in the town of Breda, the 21. of May, in the year 1660. Preached at the Walloon Church of the said town, the 23. of May, the day before His Majesties departure: by Anthony Hulsius, pastor of the said Church.</title>
                  <author>Hulsius, Antonius, 1615-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by John Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Novem 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXI --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119407:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Royal Joy. OR, A SERMON OF <hi>CONGRATVLATION</hi> Upon the five firſt Verſes of <hi>PSALM</hi> XXI.</p>
            <p>Made upon the occaſion of the firſt News of the PROCLAMATION of CHARLS II. King of Great Britain; Brought to His Majeſty in the Town of <hi> BREDA,</hi> the 21. of <hi>May,</hi> in the Year 1660.</p>
            <p>Preached at the <hi>Walloon</hi> Church of the ſaid Town, the 23. of <hi>May,</hi> the day before His Majeſties departure: By <hi>ANTHONY H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LSI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> Paſtor of the ſaid Church.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Bill, Anno</hi> 1660,</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119407:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119407:2"/>
            <head>TO HER HIGHNESS THE <hi>PRINCESS ROYAL.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon which I make bold to preſent to your Highneſs, bears upon its Front, THE ROYAL JOY, a Title given unto it by the Text; but we bear another upon the front of our hearts, <hi>viz.</hi> THE POP<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LAR JOY. The Kings Joy bath been made the Subject of the Publick Joy: It hath chiefly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Countenances of all your faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Subjects of the Town of <hi>Breda,</hi> in an
<pb facs="tcp:119407:3"/>extraordinary manner, there being none of our Inhabitants but hath given the marks of a cordial Applauſe, upon the firſt report of His Majeſties Reſtaurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with an exceſs of joy, and I dare ſay, with as ſtrong expreſsions of rejoycing, as might have been uttered by the moſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate of his own Subjects. And I may truly ſay, Madam, that it is not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time of proſperity, which hath given us the firſt impreſsions of this inclination towards that worthy Prince; it is of an older date, and had its beginning together with the knowledge we had of him: We never ſaw him coming in, or going out of this Town, during the time of his Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but we made Vows for his Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; yea, and we would have carried him upon his own Throne, had our ſtrength been equal to the motions of our hearts, and could the effects have been anſwerable to
<pb facs="tcp:119407:3"/>the tenderneſs of our affection, which hath had a not able increaſe, ſince the time Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hath favored us with the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our deſires, and hath choſen this Town to be the place where His Majeſty hath received the news of his Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where his Subjects have reſorted in crowd to render him their <hi>Devoirs,</hi> and where even our Soveraign Magistrates the Lords States General and Provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of <hi>Holland,</hi> have perſonally appeared to expreſs unto His Majeſty the ſenſe of the ſingular ſatisfaction they received by ſeeing ſuch an happy day.</p>
            <p>It is true, Madam, your Highneſs hath been the occaſion our Town hath received ſuch an Honor, and therefore we do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge you as the ſecond cauſe of it, and the Inſtrument in the hand of God; yet we do interpret it as a benefit of God, whereby he hath been pleaſed to reward the
<pb facs="tcp:119407:4"/>part we have taken, out of our affections, in the calamities of that Prince; that as for a long time we have ſympathiz'd with him, ſo we ſhould be the firſt ſharers of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and joy. I cannot think, Madam, that any one would be ſo unjuſt towards us, as to envy us ſuch an advantage, ſince it is justified even by the example of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who was pleaſed that <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> (to whom the Town of <hi>Breda</hi> may be compared upon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion) ſhould have the first ſhare of the glad tidings of his Reſurrection, which ſhe received from his own mouth, as a reward of her cares and fears for him, wherein ſhe had excelled above all his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther friends and kindred. The Custom of our Anceſtors, who rendred their memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable actions, even the days of their Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Battels, famous by the names of the places wherein they had hapned, doth give
<pb facs="tcp:119407:4"/>that right to our Town, that this ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable action of the Divine Providence, which is one of the moſt ſignal wonders that ever were celebrated by the Hiſtories of the past ages, ought to be publiſhed under its name: Bleſſed be therefore that auguſt day, wherein His Majesty being in the midſt of us, hath received by an unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous accord, the Homage of his Subjects. Let it henceforth be called, THE DAY OF <hi>BREDA:</hi> Let it be, under that Name, the Object of the Admiration of all the Christian Kings and Princes; let it ſhine even to the moſt remote places of the Barbarous Nations; let it be ingraved with the Steel in our Records and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, that for ever it may be the ſubject of the Diſcourſes of our Poſterity.</p>
            <p>But that which we do eſteem above all, Madam, is the admirable goodneſs and ſweetneſs, wherewith His Majesty hath
<pb facs="tcp:119407:5"/>received the viſits of all ſorts of perſons: Thoſe affectionate and reiterated proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and promiſes be hath made to our Soveraign Lords the States, as alſo to our vener able Magiſtrates, to the Paſtors, and to the other perſons, both Political and Eccleſiaſtical, of this Town; <hi>Of the ſincerity of his affection towards the true Reformed religion, and towards all the Proteſtant Princes and States, and chiefly towards the States of theſe Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces; promiſing unto them the continuation of the affection his Anceſtors have ſhewed unto them;</hi> and particularly, <hi>Of the favorable remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance and good will he would ſtill keep for the Town of</hi> Breda, <hi>where he had received the news of his reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and known the effects of the incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhewed to his Perſon and to his Subjects.</hi> That language, <hi>Madam,</hi> hath
<pb facs="tcp:119407:5"/>raviſhed our ſpirits, hath filled our hearts with joy, and our mouths with vows and acclamations. We have gathered it with our own ears, as the expreſsions which the <hi>Spirit of Peace</hi> had dictated to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty's mouth, which will make us hereafter caſt our eyes upon that Excellent Prince, as upon a mighty Organ reſerved by God for the preſent times, and raiſed, in his bleſsing, to be a ballance and an <hi>Equili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brium</hi> for the publick tranquillity through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And our Inhabitants, <hi>Madam,</hi> have alſo expreſſed a ſingular ſatisfaction of the gracious content his Majeſty hath been pleaſed to ſhew be hath received of their cordial affection and weak ſervices they have been able to render to thoſe that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to your Royal Houſe. And we pray your Highneſs to believe, that if the noiſe of our Muskets and Canons thundering
<pb facs="tcp:119407:6"/>from our Bulwarks, at the departure of his Maieſty, could not accompany him further then a little beyond our gates; that of our Vows and prayers to God for his proſperity, will follow him to his very City of <hi>London,</hi> and will contribute to the ſetting of his Crowns upon his head. Theſe are the trueſt proofs of our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which your Highneſs doth ever recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto us, as often as we have the honor to wait upon you, viz. <hi>thoſe of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God for your Highneſs and your Family.</hi> And truly, they are the moſt material and the moſt pure ones, and which give ſtronger impreſsions then all others; for they do aſcend to the place of origine, <hi>viz.</hi> Heaven, and bring down from thence abundance of bleſsings upon earth; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as all others do vaniſh in their pomp and apparate, and moſt part cannot bring any advantage to the object thereof. Which
<pb facs="tcp:119407:6"/>conſideration hath put me in mind of the matter of this Sermon pronounced upon the ſame day we prepared to take our leave of his Majeſty, and conceived our publick vows for the proſperity and the happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of his Voyage. Now our Flock de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring of me ſome copies of it, to keep an eternal memory in their families of ſuch an illuſtrious Occurrence, I made bold, <hi>Madam,</hi> most humbly to crave the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of your Highneſs, under whoſe ſweet &amp; favor able Government 'tis main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; being beſides doubly intereſſed in the ſubject which gave occaſion to this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, both in regard of themſelves, and in regard of his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> which is the object of our delight, and upon whoſe face the Royal luſtre of his Maiesty doth alſo ſhine. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this ſmall work be not anſwer able to its illuſtrious ſubject, yet your Highneſſ's
<pb facs="tcp:119407:7"/>goodneſs, whereof we have an infinite number of proofs, doth aſſure me you will cast a gracious eye upon the Author's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and out of your clemency will bear with his defects. In the confidence where of, I do continue my vows to the Soveraign King of Kings, that be may be pleaſed to poure his moſt precious graces upon your Highneſs, and all your Sereniſsime Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and to conſerve their Luſtre upon Earth, and make them Triumphant in Heaven: Having no other ambition but to expreſs, with all the imaginable reſpects, how much I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>MADAM, Your Highneſſe's Moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant and Subject, A. HULSIUS.</signed>
               <dateline>From <hi>BREDA,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 24. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119407:7"/>
            <head>THE ROYAL JOY. THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſalm 23. v. 1, 2, 3, 4.</bibl>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>1.</label> The King ſhall joy in thy ſtrength, O Lord, and in thy ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion how greatly ſhall be rejoice!</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>2.</label> Thou haſt given him his hearts deſire, and haſt not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden the requeſt of his lips. <hi>Selah.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <label>3.</label> For thou preventeſt him with the bleſſings of goodneſs; thou ſetteſt a crown of pure gold on his bead.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>4.</label> He asked life of thee, and thou gaveſt it him, even length of days, for ever and ever.</item>
                  </list>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>Welbeloved Brethren in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt!</opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His town, which formerly hath been the Stage on which Tragedies of War, Peſtilence and Famine, and of Bloodſhed have been acted, is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Theatre of Joy and Magnificence: A Theatre whereon an Action is now acted, which hath the whole World for Spectators. It is not a repreſentative action, ſuch as are the Comedies and Enterludes, wherein men do repreſent ſuch qualities as they really have not; but it is a real action, ſuch as were our former Tragedies, wherein the Perſons are really and indeed ſuch as they repreſent. The chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and Soveraign Actor here is the GOD of Heaven, who as he doth ſhew himſelf wonderful in all his works, ſo he doth it moſt particularly in this. You ſee your Town full of Illuſtrious perſons, of Lords, of Princes, and of Soveraign Magiſtrates: You ſee therein a KING, formerly diſpoſſeſſed of his Throne, and now ſetled again thereon, to the aſtoniſhment of all the World: You ſee the Subjects recalling their lawful Prince, out of meer affection, without conſtraint, without violence, without effuſion of blood
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119407:8"/>You ſee therein your Soveraign Magiſtrates bringing their Vows and Congratulations to the King and to his people: You ſee the fair and loving apparences of a perfect correſpondence, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n univerſd content. Upon the whole we may with truth pronounce the ſentence of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. <hi>This is the Lord's doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</hi> For, as many objects we ſee, ſo many wonders, and ſo many expreſſions of the admirable provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God; and we may with re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, that this Town hath never ſeen ſuch a day, nor is like ever to ſee ſuch a one to the worlds end. Let us ſpeak of it in publick, for it is a work which is done in publick, and it foundeth to the very extremities of the earth: Let us ſpeak of it in the houſe of God, ſince it is the work of God: Let us ſpeak of it in bleſſing, ſince God hath wrought it, not in wrath, as he ſometimes wrought here, but in his grace; Let us ſpeak of it in the day of our reſt, ſince he hath done it for the ſetling of the peace and reſt of his Church. Let us therefore call this day, <hi>The day of the Lord;</hi> and let us ſay yet with the ſame Pſalmiſt, <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made, let us rejoice and be glad in it.</hi> But let S. <hi>Paul</hi> tell us the occaſion of that joy, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>It is now the time accepted, it is now the day of ſalvation.</hi> A day of ſalvation indeed, and an accepted time: A day of ſalvation for the King; a day of ſalvation for his people; a day of ſalvation for the true Reformed Religion; and an accepted time for our State and for us all together. Both the joy, and the ground of it, are found in our preſent Text, which hath for an object two general parts. I. <hi>A joyful King.</hi> II. The cauſe of his joy, viz. <hi>His ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and deliverance.</hi> And this cauſe is more largely deducted, 1. By its Author and principal cauſe, which is <hi>the ſtrength of the Lord.</hi> 2. By its ſecondary cauſe, or the means whereby the King hath obtained his deliverance, namely, <hi>his hearts deſire,</hi> and the prayer or <hi>request of his lips.</hi> 3. By its effects or the proofs of his deliverance, which are, I. General, <hi>That he hath prevented him with the bleſſings of goodneſs.</hi> II. Particular, viz. I. <hi>The ſetting of the Crown.</hi> II. <hi>The lengthening of days.</hi> This is the diviſion of the Text.</p>
            <p>But it is to be obſerved, that this place is one of thoſe that can admit of three ſenſes ordinarily applied to the holy Scriptures. I. The literal ſenſe. II. The myſtical ſenſe. III, The accommodated
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119407:8"/>ſenſe. The literal is that which is immediately and properly the intention of the holy Ghoſt, be it found either in ſimple and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per words, or in figurative tearms. The myſtical ſenſe is that which is known to be the ſecondary intention of the holy Ghoſt, and hath no place but in Types onely. 1. When the thing ſpoken of is found accompliſhed in ſome ſubjects, which was a Type or figure of Chriſt, or of his Church. 2. When what is ſaid to belong to the myſtical ſenſe in one place, is found to appertain to the literal ſenſe in another. Whenſoever any of thoſe two conditions is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the myſtical ſenſe is not admitted, and we ought ſingly to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to to the litteral, which then is to have place alone, without looking therein for any ſecondary intention. We might illuſtrate this by Examples, but the preſent occaſion doth not permit it. The accommodated ſenſe is never under the intention of the holy Ghoſt, as to any particular place, but only as to the whole ſcope of the whole Scripture, and is left to the liberty of the Expoſitor, who may draw out of it all manner of moralities for the publick inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſo as he keep within the bounds of the Analogy of Faith grounded upon the word of God. We ſay then, that as to the literal ſenſe, our Text belongs to King <hi>David;</hi> as to the myſtical ſenſe, it belongs to the Kings of Kings, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and as to the accommodated ſenſe, it belongs to this Kings Who is the Preſent ſubject of the publick admiration; And we ſhall, with the aſſiſtance of the grace of God, expound by that triple ſenſe, keeping ſtill within the diviſion already made of it.</p>
            <div n="1" type="sense">
               <head>I. The Literal ſenſe.</head>
               <p>THe Rabbines among the Hebrews do expound that Pſalm two ways. Some upon the ground of the Hiſtory, do apply it to King <hi>David;</hi> others upon the ground of the Prophecy, do apply it to King Meſſiah, as R. <hi>David Kimchi</hi> upon the Pſalms doth witneſs: We do imbrace both theſe Expoſitions, referring it to King <hi>David</hi> in the litteral ſenſe, and to the King Meſſiah in the miſtical ſenſe, as we have declared. It is a Pſalm of Thankſgiving, which <hi>David</hi> makes unto God, the ſubject whereof is not expreſſed in the Title; but if we conſider the Contents and the matter of it,, we may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily conjecture that he hath ſung that acknowledgment unto God,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119407:9"/>about the beginning of his Reign, after the time of his affliction: The Crown had been deſigned for him upon the ſecond year of the Reign of <hi>Saul,</hi> when he was anointed by <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet to be King in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but he could not enjoy it during <hi>Sauls</hi> time, who perſecuted him from place to place: So that he hath been the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of all manner of adverſities for the ſpace of nine or ten years; namely, until the death of <hi>Saul,</hi> at which time he was anointed the ſecond time, and was exalted upon the Throne at that time then, when God had accompliſhed the days of his calamities, and had delivered him from the hands of his perſecutors, and had ſet the Crown upon his head, he compoſed that Pſalm of Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving unto God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. You ſee then therein <hi>a Joyful King,</hi> yea, and <hi>greatly rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing.</hi> The original Text expreſſeth two Verbs, whereof the one ſignifies the joy of the hearts, and the other the joy of the forehead, <hi>viz.</hi> when it ſhews it ſelf by the outward geſtures, as doth ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily an exceſſive joy. And truly that of <hi>David</hi> ought to have been of that nature, conſidering the notable change of his condition from one extream to the other, from the extremity of calamity to the extremity of luſtre and glory. But there are two ſorts of joy in the Kings and Princes of this world, an evil and carnal joy, and a joy which is good and approved of God: Their carnal and bad joy is, when they do rejoyce alone, their Subjects not being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of their joy: Such was the joy of <hi>Ahaſhuerus,</hi> and of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Eſther</hi> 3.15. <hi>The King and</hi> Haman <hi>ſat down to drink; but the City</hi> Shuſhan <hi>was perplexed.</hi> Such is alſo the joy of all the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, who do forget <hi>Tyberius</hi> his leſſon, which permits indeed to ſhear the ſheep, but not to flay them: But <hi>Davids</hi> joy was a joy rebounding upon the foreheads of his people. The near con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction that is between the King and his Subjects, as between the head and the members of the body, can ſuffer no alternative as to their rejoycing; if it be juſt, it is reciprocal: That of the King can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hold without that of the Subjects, nor that of the Subjects with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that of their King. The Kings being exalted upon their Thrones, are as the Sun in Heaven, which is not ſeated in that high luſtre, that by the ſplendor of his beams he might dazzle the eyes of men, but that he might communicate his light to the Stars, and his heat to the Earth, and give to all the Creatures he doth illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119407:9"/>a pleaſing aſpect, and a ſmiling look. The Pſalmiſt doth ſignifie ſo much, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Thou haſt made him moſt bleſſed for ever.</hi> It is a property which doth accompany the good Kings, to be made <hi>most bleſſed,</hi> not only for a paſſive bleſſing, relating only to their own perſons, that they might acknowledge themſelves bleſſed by the Dominion and Power they have upon the people, but for an active bleſſing alſo relating to the people, that they might likewiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge themſelves to be happy and bleſſed by the good and wiſe conduct of their Kings: So the joy becomes reciprocal, and is approved of God, when it is limited by that joy of the people, <hi>viz.</hi> when the people is partaker of the joy of their King, and the King is ſharer of the affliction of his people. That that of <hi>David</hi> hath been of that nature, it hath appeared in all his actions, carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf towards his Subjects, as a Faithful Shepherd towards his Sheep, for ſo alſo he calls them, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. when he preſented himſelf with his whole Family to the edge of the ſword of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Angel, to cauſe the plague of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ceaſe.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The <hi>Cauſe</hi> of his Joy hath been his <hi>Deliverance,</hi> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs whereof may be known by the two aforementioned extreams, <hi>viz.</hi> the preceding calamity, and the preſent felicity. He had been wandering the ſpace of nine or ten years, hunted and perſecuted from one place to another, no reſt in any place, every where ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to a thouſand dangers and ambuſcadoes: And as St. <hi>Paul</hi> faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. That he hath been <hi>in perils by his own Countreymen, in perils by the Heathen, in perils in the City, in perils in the Wilderneſs, in wearineſs and painfulneſs, in watchings often, in hunger and thirſt, in faſtings often, in cold and nakedneſs.</hi> This King hath gone through the ſame Fortune, not finding any ſafe retreat, purſued by his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies through the Wilderneſs, betrayed by his own Countreymen, diſcovered in the Towns of the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> often compelled to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe himſelf to eſcape and flee in the middle of the night, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into the Dens and Rocks: Yea, ſometimes he hath been brought to ſuch neceſſity, that for want of Victuals, he hath been forced to eat the Shewbread, conſecrated unto God, and hath ſubſiſted by the Preſents ſent him by <hi>Abigal,</hi> a vertuous woman. See 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21. and 25. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> God having then delivered him miraculouſly from all thoſe dangers and inconveniences, having ſetled him King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> having put the Scepter into his hand, and the Crown upon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119407:10"/>his head; ſee whether he had not cauſe to call that a remarkable deliverance, and ſo be exceedingly joyful. But he is not content to acknowledge himſelf delivered; he ſhews us further, the Author, the means, and the effects of this deliverance.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>The Author</hi> of his deliverance is <hi>the Lord,</hi> who by <hi>his ſtrength</hi> had exalted him; therefore he doth not ſay, <hi>my deliverance,</hi> but <hi>thy deliverance.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, that it was not a deliverance obtained by his own dexterity and conduct, or by the ſtrength of his arms, as it hath often happened, that by victorious arms and bloody battels, illuſtrious men have made to themſelves a way to the Crown, and have conquered Kingdoms. But <hi>David</hi> doth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute his deliverance ſolely to the ſtrength of God. And indeed he was proclaimed King after <hi>Savls</hi> death, by the meer affection of the people, having had no need of compelling them by his arms to yield him obedience. And truly thoſe kinds of deliverances that come immediately from the hand of God, are the beſt; and the Scepters which God puts into the hands of Princes without ſhedding of blood, as <hi>David</hi> had his, are far more excellent then thoſe they do ſnatch themſelves by violence of arms. And that for four reaſons. 1. The joy for it is purer, and more univerſal. In the violent Conqueſts, the joy of the Prince and of the people cannot be ſo perfect, but they muſt needs ſee ſome afflicted Widows that have loſt their Husbands in the Fight; ſome Children crying and lamenting the death of their Fathers; and ſome Fathers and Mothers weeping for the loſs of their Children. But ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts as come immediately from the hand of God, are not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to any calamities of that nature. 2. The Peoples <hi>approbation</hi> is more manifeſt. The violent conqueſts are often againſt the people's good will, who ſubmit themſelves to the yoke, not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but out of neceſſity. The contrary is ſeen, when the people themſelves, by the direction of the ſole providence of God, who hath the hearts of men in his mighty hand, doth ſet their Prince on the throne. That cannot be done but with a general applauſe, and with all the viſible apparences of a flouriſhing and peaceable Reign. 3. The <hi>confidence and truſt</hi> that a Prince ſo delivered and exalted, puts in his God, is greater, when he doth acknowledge with humility, that it hath been the right hand of God which hath done that wonder, without contributing thereunto his own
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119407:10"/>power and induſtry. You ſee that in <hi>David, Pſ.</hi> 20. <hi>Some trust in chariots, and ſome in horſes, but we will remember the name of the Lord our God.</hi> And <hi>Pſ.</hi> 44. <hi>I will not truſt in my bowe, neither ſhall my ſword ſave me; but thou ſhalt ſave us from our enemies, and ſhalt put them to ſhame that hate us.</hi> 4. His <hi>lustre</hi> is the more eminent: His ſubjects look upon him as upon the mirror of Gods favor, and do with obedience ſubmit to his ſcepter, ſeeing it is God who cauſeth him ro reign. His <hi>Enemies</hi> are afraid of him and do flie from him, learning to ſay with <hi>Balaam,</hi> Numb. 23. <hi>The Lord his God is with him, and the ſhout of a King is among them.</hi> His <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> do honor him as Gods Anointed, and do ſeek his amity and alliance, as did <hi>Abimilech</hi> King of <hi>Gerar,</hi> Gen. 26. coming to the Patriarch <hi>Iſaac,</hi> who told him, <hi>Wherefore come ye to me, ſeeing ye hate me, and have ſent me away from you? Abimelech</hi> anſwered him, <hi>We ſaw certainly that the Lord was with thee, and we ſaid, Let there be now an oath betwixt us, even betwixt us and thee, and let us make a covenant with thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Means</hi> whereby <hi>David</hi> came to that felicity, hath been <hi>his hearts deſire,</hi> and <hi>the requeſt of his lips,</hi> that is, his ardent Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. The Communion he hath had with God during the time of his affliction, is known by the Titles of ſeveral Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lms. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed 3. at that time when he was flying before <hi>Abſalom</hi> his ſon, the 34. when he was expelled by <hi>Abim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lech;</hi> the 52. when he was diſcovered unto <hi>Saul</hi> by <hi>Doeg</hi> the <hi>Jdumean,</hi> the 56. being taken by the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> at <hi>Gath,</hi> the 57. and the 142. in his flight from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Saul,</hi> hiding himſelf in the Den; the 59. when <hi>Saul</hi> ſent to kill him, the 63. being in the Wilderneſs of <hi>Judah</hi>; the 102. is a Pſalm of complaint made by him unto God in his extream per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity and diſtreſs. All theſe holy meditations do teſtifie the Piety of that King, and ſhew whom he had recourſe unto in his calamity, <hi>viz.</hi> to God, who hath alſo heard him at length, and hath granted him the deſires of his ſoul: For Prayer is the Key, and openeth that which is ſhut by men; and Godlineſs hath the promiſe of the life that is now, and of that which is to come. But it is to be obſerved, that among all the expreſſions uſed by him in his Pſalms, not one can be found, wherein he directly demands the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or ſhews the le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st token of impatience for the long continuance of his afflictions; but he doth meerly repreſent the ſtate of his c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119407:11"/>and with an admirable temper of truſt and patience, doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer all to the providence of God, and prayeth only for the ſupport of his grace, and for the peace of his Church: Thereby teaching us, that it is not the leaſt of Gods graces, when he is pleaſed we ſhould ſuffer for his glory, that we be able to refrain the deſires of our hearts, and the expreſſions of our lips, that nothing that is ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular may eſcape from them, that may tend to the diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dvantage of his ſervice, and of the obedience we do owe unto him. He teaches us likewiſe which are the true Prayers, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the deſires of the heart, and the attention of the ſoul, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be expreſſed by the lips: Otherwiſe they are as the found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing braſs, or a tinkling cymbal, i. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Effects</hi> and the <hi>Proofs</hi> of his deliverance have two parts. The I is general, and doth conſiſt in <hi>being prevented with the ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſings of goodneſs.</hi> God, in delivering of him, hath prevented him two ſeveral ways. 1. As to the time, 2. as to the means. 1. As to the time: For he had only <hi>asked life,</hi> to eſcape ſafe out of the hands of <hi>Saul,</hi> who perſecuted him unto death: And behold, not only he delivered him, and preſerved his life, but alſo he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented him with a bleſſing he expected not yet, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Saul</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing killed in the Battel againſt the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> the door was opened to him to the Crown, and he not only found means to breathe a little from his troubles, and to live, but alſo to live ſecurely, long and happily. 2. As to the means, no doubt but <hi>David</hi> thought he was to conquer the Kingdom which God had promiſed to him, by ſtrength of Arms; but God prevented him in that thought, and not only made him Maſter of the Towns, but alſo of the hearts of his ſubjects: For it is ſaid, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>And the men of Judah came, and there they anointed</hi> David <hi>King over the houſe of</hi> Judah. So doth God hear the prayers of his own children, giving them or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily more then they do ask. The II. particular end is, I. The ſetting upon him the Crown, <hi>Thou ſetteſt a Crown of pure Gold on his head, viz.</hi> the Crown of <hi>Saul,</hi> which was brought to him from the Battel, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.10. By which words the Royal Dignity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God had honored him is ſignified. Note that he faith, God had ſet on him that Crown, and not men, nor he himſelf. True it is, that men are thoſe that ſet Crowns on the heads of Kings; but when God doth not put his hand to it, they are not well ſet. He is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119407:11"/>that great Maſter, who alone doth underſtand the Trade and the Art of ſetting Crowns, who can ſo well ſettle th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m on the heads of Princes, that they keep firm and will not fall. Men may meddle with it, but without the heavenly favour and aſſiſtance, they cannot ſucceed well therein: As experience hath ſhewed it in all ages, that Crowns either uſurped, or unjuſtly ſnatched, ſet on by Sedition and Rebellion, have fallen with thoſe that went about to wear them: For it is too heavy a burthen, and not to be born by every one, but by ſuch only as God calls thereunto, and in bles for it. 2. The lengthening of days; <hi>Thou gaveſt him length of days for ever and ever.</hi> The years of the life of <hi>David</hi> amounted to ſeventy, and thoſe of his reign to forty: For he reigned ſeven years in <hi>Hebron</hi> and thirty three in <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> a lengthning of days conſiderable enough, which he durſt not hope for during the time of his perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions; but at the beginning of his reign, by the gift of Prophecy, he promiſed it unto himſelf. And what hath been wanting, as to the perpetuity of it mentioned here, hath been made good by the lengthning of days of eternity in heaven above; which is the true life of the faithful. But this ſeems rather to belong to the Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſenſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="sense">
               <head>II. The Myſtical ſenſe:</head>
               <p>FRom the Literal ſenſe we come to the Myſtical. <hi>David</hi> was the Type of Jeſus Chriſt; and therefore what is ſaid of the one, may be referred or applied to the other; yet ſtill obſerving that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral rule, that the myſtical ſenſe takes onely place in ſuch matters wherein the thing is verified in both, that is to ſay, that what is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken myſtically in one place, be found literally in another place, as we have declared before: So that all the parts that cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly verified in the Antitype, do remain ſolely appropriated in the literal ſenſe to the Type, without paſting to the myſtical ſenſe. And mutually ſuch as cannot be verified in the Type, do remain ſolely appropriated in the literal ſenſe to the Antitype, without paſſing to the myſtical ſenſe: For then the Holy Ghoſt does pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the literal ſenſe in figurate words, the Type being ſet down for the Antitipe. Upon this account let us expound this Text, as all others of the like nature: But at this time we ſhall only trace
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119407:12"/>the introdnction of that relation between the Type and his Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type: For our Lord Jeſus Chriſt being the ordinary ſubject of our meditations, the more large deduction of that matter is often enough made upon other occaſions.</p>
               <p n="1">I. The <hi>joyful King</hi> is the King <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> not he of the Rabbines, a meer carnal and imaginary <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> but Jeſus Chriſt the object of all the ancient Types and Prophecies. This joy is <hi>great,</hi> ſince the ſubject of it is <hi>great,</hi> it is perfectly <hi>pure,</hi> ſuitable to the holy Soul of Jeſus Chriſt, which is not expreſſed by outward geſtures of exultation, as that of men, which is more carn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. It is <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative:</hi> for that King knows of no other joy, but ſuch as is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to his Church; yea, he rather came to the world for the joy of his people, then for his own, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. <hi>I bring you good tidings of great joy which ſhall be to all the people.</hi> Matth. 1. <hi>For be ſhall ſave his people from their ſins.</hi> And what he faith <hi>John</hi> 11.15. <hi>I am glad for your ſakes,</hi> we may apply it to the end and aim of his exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The <hi>Cauſe</hi> of his joy is the deliverance of the ſtate of his exinanition, and of the ſufferings both of his ſoul and body, Eſ. 53.8. <hi>He was taken from priſon and from judgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Author</hi> of his deliverance is God, who through his ſtrength hath exalted him, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.19, 20. <hi>According to the working of his mighty power, which he wrought in Chriſt, when he raiſed him from the dead,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Means</hi> is his hearts deſire, and the requeſt of his lips: The prayers of Jeſus Chriſt during the time of his humiliation, have been frequent; and although he had the revelation of the eternal Decree of God touching himſelf, yet he hath prayed unto him for the accompliſhing of it, <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>Father glorifie thy ſon, that thy Son alſo may glorifie thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The proofs of his deliverance are likewiſe obvious. 1. Alſo the <hi>general</hi> part, that he hath been <hi>prevented with bleſſings,</hi> hath ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther been true in the Type, then in Jeſus Chriſt; for to ſpeak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, he hath been prevented with no kinde of bleſſings in the the ſtate of his exaltation, neither for himſelf nor for his Church, which before he had not fore ſeen and foretold: And in that point, as in many other, he being God and Man, and Mediator between God and men, ought to be diſtinguiſhed from all others. 2. As
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119407:12"/>to the <hi>particulars.</hi> 1. The ſetting on of the Crown, yea, and of a Crown of pure Gold: it ſignifies here the Royal Office, wherein he wears a Crown that ſurmounts, and is more excellent then the Crowns of all the Kings of the earth: For <hi>God hath highly exalted him, and hath given him a name which is above every name,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. <hi>Far above all Principalities and Powers, and might,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and hath put all things under his feet, and gave him to be the head over all things to the Church,</hi> &amp;c. 2. The <hi>lengthening</hi> of days, even for ever and ever, is rather verified in Chriſt, then in <hi>David</hi> his Type, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>Chriſt being raiſed from the dead, dieth no more, death hath no more dominion over him.</hi> Eſ. 53. <hi>He ſhall prolong his days; who ſhall declare his generation?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="sense">
               <head>III. The Accommodated Senſe.</head>
               <p>IF we compare the example of that King who is the preſent ſubject of our admiration, with King <hi>David,</hi> as to thoſe things we have ſpoken of him, we ſhall finde them extreamly like one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the other. We do not intend here to fall upon Panegyricks and praiſes of the vertues and excellent qualities of that Prince, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a thing neither ſuitable to our perſons, nor to this place, which is the Chair of truth and ſimplicity, and not of flattery. But our deſign is only to ſhew you that admirable conformity that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe two Kings, and to pray God for this, that he might be pleaſed to grant him the grace to acknowledge that his delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance comes from him alone, as you ſee he hath done unto <hi>David.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. The <hi>joyful King</hi> is KING CHARLS, Second of that name, lately Proclaimed by the favour and grace of GOD, KING OF GREAT BRITAIN, FRANCE AND IRELAND, DEFENDER OF THE TRUE FAITH, THE LAWFUL HEIR OF THE CROWN, FROM THE VERY DAY OF THE DEATH OF CHARLS THE FIRST HIS FATHER OF GLORIOUS MEMORY. If <hi>David</hi> hath greatly rejoyced, even unto exultation, I leave it to you to judge whether this King hath not had reaſon to rejoyce too, his fortune having been like unto that of <hi>David.</hi> Although we have been told, that when the firſt news came to him of it, no kinde of alteration upon his face, nor any motion in his ſpirit was obſerved. The reaſon of it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119407:13"/>cauſe the violent ſhakings of the calamities happened to that Prince one upon another during ſuch a long ſeries of years, have r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſed his ſpirit above all earthly things, to look on them all with an equal countenance, and have taught him to ſhew himſelf im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable to the attempts of either the good or bad fortune: As the iron, the end whereof is hardned in the fire by being often put therein, whether you try it upon a ſtone, or upon a maſs of gold, it remains ſtill inflexible. But that commendable moderation could by no means hinder him from receiving in his ſoul a very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſatisfaction of the ſingular grace of God to him, in inclining the hearts of his Subjects to their duty towards him, nor from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing a joy ſuitable to the due acknowledgement of that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable benefit of God. Likewiſe, there is no doubt but that the joy of that Prince is a lawful joy, and approved of by God, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mixed with that joy of his Subjects, whom we ſee to be as joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for having yielded themſelves to their lawful King, as the King himſelf may be joyful for being reſtored to his Subjects. From whence we conceive this good Omen, that ſince it is God who hath raiſed this joy, it will remain ever common and reciprocal for the time to come, ſuch as his faithful Subjects could never be ſo happy as to take theſe ten or twelve years bypaſt, when all the joy was confined in the breaſt of an Uſurper of the Kingly Dignity, and of thoſe of his faction, which filled the Kingdom with violence, the Political Government with confuſion and diſorders, and the Church with Sects and Hereſies, the ſmaller fort of the people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oppreſſed, and the great ones carrying their heads to be cut off upon Scaffolds: Judge ye what may then have been the joy of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men, when none durſt open his mouth in the behalf of the good Cauſe, without incurring the crime of High Treaſon, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, but againſt an Uſurped Authority, and without expoſing themſelves to the loſs both of life and eſtate. Therefore do you repreſent unto your ſelves the joy and the action of that people, to be like to the joy of thoſe Northern people, who for ſix moneths together having not ſeen the ſun, aſſoon as they ſpie the firſt dawning of the day above their Horizon, after a long and thick darkneſs, they run to meet that fair Planet, and climb upon the mountains, to be illuminated by his beams ſo long hidden from them; and as the joy of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> returning from <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119407:13"/>Pſal.</hi> 126. <hi>When the Lord turned again the captivity of Zion, we were like them that dream; then was our mouth filled with laughter, and our tongue with ſinging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. The cauſe of his joy, is his deliverance; which we may ſay to have been as great as that of <hi>David,</hi> for it goes from one extreme unto the other, as well as his. But I am diſpenſed by many conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations from making here unto you a full Narrative of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities and ſad travels of that Prince during the twelve years of his baniſhment: And the chiefeſt reaſon of my ſilence therein, ſhall be my ignorance. For although we have had often the honor to ſee him in this town, and upon thoſe occaſions we have heard with much ſorrow of heart ſeveral relations of his adverſities; yet knowing all theſe only by hear-ſay, and the certainty and the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances being unknown to us, it is not proper for us to ſay any thing of that here. Beſides, it being a day of rejoycing, it would not be convenient to wrong our ſelves ſo much, as to deprive us, by ſuch melancholy diſcourſes, of thoſe chaſte pleaſures, whereunto our Bonfires, the ringing of our Bells, and the ſhooting off our Canons do invite us, in the admiration of Gods wonders in the deliverance of that Prince. Adde thereunto, that the little we have ſpoken of <hi>David's</hi> afflictions, not being taken out of any Sermon, but only one of the Books of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> it would be in vain for me to undertake to compriſe in a Sermon limited by the time of one hour, all the ſad occurrences of above twelve years time, whereof your poſterity will ſee hereafter many very volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous Hiſtories, no leſs remarkable then thoſe of former ages. It may for this time ſuffice, you ſee in this town before your own eyes an Object, which an hundred years hence (if the world con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues ſo long) will be the ſubject of Table and Journey-diſcourſes, and ſo much admired as now adays the moſt illuſtrious men, celebrated by the Hiſtories, may be by us. A Prince of the moſt illuſtrious Blood in all <hi>Europe,</hi> of an extraction meerly Royal of the Father and Mothers ſide, diſpoſſeſſed of his Inheritance, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from his Country, abandoned by his own Blood, wandring among Foreign Nations: who was accounted to be forgotten of God, becauſe out of the Worlds memory, whoſe manner is to turn its back to Adverſity, though innocent, and to adore nothing but Proſperity, although never ſo guilty. But who hath been miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119407:14"/>delivered from the reproach, and reſtored into the poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Anceſtors, contrary to all humane apparences.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Author</hi> then of this deliverance cannot be other then God, whoſe hand and <hi>ſtrength</hi> only hath wrought that wonder. So that this King may very well ſay with <hi>David, Thy deliverance,</hi> having gotten it not by the ſtrength of his arms, but by the only direction from above: God having put into his hands the bodies and the hearts of his Subjects, who were as wandering ſheep ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their ſhepherd. An example, wherein it ſeems God hath undertaken to give a publick check to the unworthineſs of our age, for a memorial and an inſtruction to poſterity; that the Great ones of this world having forſaken the juſt cauſe of that Prince, He himſelf alone hath been willing to ſhew he is the Protector of innocency, <hi>who raiſeth up the poor out of the duſt, and lifteth the needy out of the dunghill, Pſ.</hi> 113.7. Yea, he hath ſo wrought therein, that he hath ſhewed it was his own work, and not of men, taking from them all pretence of partaking in that glory, that that Prince might be beholding to him alone, and not to any foreign force, which would have rendred the deliverance ſo much the leſs il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious, and the conqueſt the leſs glorious. Glorious was the conqueſt of the Earl of <hi>Richmond</hi> (afterwards <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh) when he went out of <hi>Normandy</hi> with a ſmall Army into <hi>England</hi> againſt <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, Tyrant, a Murderer, and an Uſurper of the Crown, and won the Kingdom with the loſs of an hundred men only, the ſubjects wiſhing nothing more then to be delivered from the hand of the Tyrant. But the deliverance of <hi>Charles II.</hi> hath been Divine, who hath conquered without fighting or loſing one man: God alone having fought for him with inviſible arms, not againſt the bodies, but againſt the ſouls of men, making them ſubject to his obedience.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>means</hi> hath been, <hi>his hearts deſire, and the requeſt of his lips.</hi> Let him go to ſea, who will learn to pray, faith the proverb. No doubt but that Prince, in the midſt of the vaſt ſea of his cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, among ſo many ſtorms that went over his head, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of all ſupply from men, hath had his recourſe unto the Lord, the only ſupport of the afflicted ſouls, and ſaid often with <hi>David, Out of the depths do I cry unto thee, O Lord!</hi> and with queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> when ſhe was carried from the Tower of <hi>London</hi> to the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119407:14"/>priſon of <hi>Woodſtock,</hi> by order of queen <hi>Mary</hi> her ſiſter, <hi>Be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful unto me, O God, be merciful unto me, for my ſoul truſteth in thee; yea in the ſhadow of thy wings do I make my refuge, until the calamity be overpaſt.</hi> In a word, the Lord hath heard the deſire of his heart, and hath rewarded his perſevering piety in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Reformed religion, which he ſtedfaſtly kept in his heart, notwithſtanding wait hath been often laid to his conſcience, during the years of his baniſhment among the enemies of the Truth: deceitful promiſes could not ſhake the ſtedfaſtneſs of his ſpirit: Yet he hath been forced to ſwallow down the blame with the calamity, as if he had been unfaithful to God therein. But ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath ſhewed the contrary, that although he was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with the thick clouds of Idolatry, he hath ever preſerved the purity of the worſhip of God in his family; as a moſt learned and moſt orthodox Divine, among his Domeſticks, an unreproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able witneſs before God and man, hath aſſured us. Yea, and the event doth now ſhew us the contrary. <hi>David faith, Pſal.</hi> 66.18. <hi>If I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear me.</hi> So, had this Prince had any thought tending to the diſadvantage of the Worſhip of God, and of that flouriſhing Church of Chriſt in his Kingdoms, the Lord would not have heard the deſire of his heart. But he hath heard it: And therefore let us conclude that his conſcience and his affection to the truth of the holy Goſpel remained pure and ſincere, as he hath alſo proteſted in the midſt of us. A mighty argument to prove that God honoreth ſuch as do honor him, and are faithful to his ſervice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>proofs</hi> of his deliverance are likewiſe manifeſt. I. In general, <hi>God hath prevented him with bleſsings.</hi> The world did imagine that new Form of the Government of thoſe Kingdoms to have taken root; that the wound of that Revolution was now conſolidated, and that the ugly skar it had contracted, could not be opened but by the edge of the ſword. But God's thoughts are not as mens thoughts: <hi>As the Heavens are higher then the earth, ſo are the ways of God higher then the ways of men,</hi> Iſa. 55. Who untying and unfolding all thoſe difficulties, hath opened to this Prince a door whereat he hoped not to be able to enter, when he thought upon the way of Arms; wherein the Grace from above hath prevented him, ſhewing him a ſurer, an eaſier, and a ſafer
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119407:15"/>way for him and for his people. II. In particular. 1. <hi>He bath ſet a Crown upon his head;</hi> yea, and three Crowns are deſigned unto him. And what is more, it is God who ſetteth them on his head, who by his mighty hand raiſeth the hands of his ſubjects to ſet them, with an unanimous conſent, upon his head. Wherein his providence is yet more admirable, then it hath been in the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>David,</hi> ſithence the Crown of <hi>Saul,</hi> taken up in the battel, was brought to <hi>David</hi> by an <hi>Amalekite,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. after the ſame manner as that of <hi>Richard</hi> the 3. of whom we have ſpoken before, was ſet on <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. his head in the Battel-field; both by antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation: Whereas to this Prince it is offered after a mature deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration of all his States. To <hi>David</hi> it was preſented, he being in the Kingdom; to this, he being yet abroad. <hi>David</hi> was only proclaimed <hi>King of Judah,</hi> at the beginning of his reign, for the other Tribes adhered yet to the ſon of <hi>Saul</hi> for two years: But this is proclaimed <hi>King of all his Kingdoms,</hi> without any oppoſition. 2. The <hi>lengthening of days</hi> ſhall be the crowning of that admirable work of God, which as <hi>David,</hi> by the gift of prophefie, promiſed unto himſelf, ſo do we wiſh it to this Prince by our vows and prayers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="instruction">
               <head>INSTRUCTION.</head>
               <p>SOme might here ſay the ſame that ſometimes one <hi>Sheba the ſon of Bichri</hi> ſaid, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.1. <hi>We have no part in</hi> David. the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of this King and of his Subjects, is not our intereſt; their joy is not our joy, who live under, and depend on other Magiſtrates, and therefore have nothing common. I anſwer, it is true, that as the Sea doth divide us, ſo there is a diverſity of Politick Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between us. But there is another union beſides that of the bodies, viz. that of conſciences, whereby this Prince and his people do acknowledge themſelves to be tied unto us, and our Soveraign Magiſtrates and their Subjects do acknowledge to be tied unto them. There are two ſeveral ties that binde us to our Superiors, each Nation to their own; but there is one only tie that ties us all to the King of Kings, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: as ſeveral lines drawn from the circumference of the circle, do meet all in the centre which is in the middle; ſo Jeſus Chriſt and the purity of the holy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119407:15"/>Goſpel is our common centre wherein we meet together, as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame body, as Subjects of the ſame King, as Citizens of the ſame Spiritual Commonwealth. So we have part in <hi>David,</hi> ſo this King and his people are near related to us: our intereſts are common, our joyes common, our advantages common, our loſſes common. And upon this account we pour this day our Prayers for that Prince,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That God the pleaſed to accompliſh in and for him the excellen work be hath begun: That be will lead him in his journey, and bring him ſafe into his Kingdom, to incline the hearts of all his ſubjects to him, that all of them, none excepted; may imbrace him as their Father and Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer: ſo to ſettle his Crown upon his Head, that it may never be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hereafter. To ſtrengthen him againſt all foreign forces: to protect him againſt the deſigns of his enemies, againſt all dangers and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, and to give him a flouriſhing and peaceable Reign; that being made a joyful and contented King ſitting upon his Throne, he might all the days of his life acknowledge the Author and the manner of his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, Religiouſly remember the gracious Protection of god, during the long tempeſt of his calamities, and the wonders he hath wrought for his reſtauration: That be might keep a holy correſpondence with the State of theſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces, as his Anceſtors have done, and might ſhew the firſt effects of his acknowledgement, by a fervent zeal to the repurgation of the Church of Jeſus Chriſt, of all thoſe Sects and Hereſies that have crept into that Kingdom, and have been the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of Rebellion during the times of confuſion: Therein imitating</hi> David <hi>King of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>whoſe firſt care was at the beginning of his Reign to take order that the Ark of God might reſt in an honorable and decent place. And the Queen,</hi> Elizabeth <hi>of glorious memory, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun her Reign by the Reformation of the Church, which was then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the Tyrannical zeal of her ſiſter Queen</hi> Mary; <hi>who upon thoſe ſteps have made their Reigns happy and peaceable, the one of forty, and the other of forty five years. We wiſh unto that King the ſame ardor for the glory of God, and a lengthening of days beyond that. And that having long and happy worn the three Corwns upon earth, the King of Kings be pleaſed to ſet the fourth upon his head in heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>God grant him that grace.</closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119407:16"/>
            <head>A SPEECH made to the KING in the Caſtle of <hi>BREDA,</hi> BY <hi>ANTHONY HULSIUS</hi> Paſtor, In the Name and in the preſence of the Conſiſtory of the WALLOON Church.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE know this day by experience, that it is God who makes Kings, and doth ſet Crowns on their heads. The example of your Majeſty doth afford us a very clear proof of it, which cauſeth the admiration of the whole world, and fills with joy and content the hearts of your faithful Subjects. We who have the honor of ſeeing the preſence of your Majeſty in the midſt of us, in this happy conjuncture, are partakers of their joy, and have this day bleſſed the name of the Lord for it; giving thanks to his fatherly providence, that having pulled down a Protector raiſed upon falſe grounds, he hath been pleaſed to reſtore the true Protector to his People, and Religion to its true Defender. And as your Majeſty hath ſhewed your pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in receiving the Vows and Congratulations of three of the Colledges of this Town, that came before us: We moſt humbly pray your Majeſty to have the ſame good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the fourth and laſt, namely, that of the Governors of the <hi>Walloon</hi> Church, who come to proſtrate themſelves at the feet of your Majeſty, and to offer you the four Vows or Prayers they do make for your Proſperity, <hi>viz.</hi> A Vow of <hi>Piety,</hi> a Vow of <hi>Felicity,</hi> a Vow of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and a Vow of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which are the four eminent qualities of your
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119407:16"/>Glorious and Illuſtrious Anceſtors. The Piety of King <hi>Edward</hi> the VI. the firſt truly Reformed King, both as to his Life, and as to his Faith, and the firſt Reformer of the Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Felicity of Queen</hi> Elizabeth, who according to the teſtimony of her ſucceſſor, King <hi>James</hi> your Majeſties Grandfather, hath ſurmounted in prudence and happineſs of Government, all the Monarchs of this world ſince <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar.</hi> A Lady who hath tryed a fortune like to that of your Majeſty, who was taken from the Priſon to the Crown, and by a wondrous tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature and mixture of Courage, Prudence, Severity and Meekneſs, was made the object of the love and fear of her Subjects, and the miracle of her age, during the ſpace of forty five years. The <hi>Wiſdom of King</hi> James, whoſe mouth was the Oracle of the Learned men of his time. The <hi>Juſtice</hi> of King <hi>Charls</hi> the firſt, of glorious memory, your Majeſties Father, a meek and juſt Prince, whom I have had the honor to ſee upon his Throne, and to paſs a part of my life under his peaceable Reign, until the time of the late unhappy confuſions; which your Majeſty having now ſurmounted by the grace of God, and that fatal ſtorm being now over, we ſee abundance of new bleſſings from above, coming down upon your Majeſties perſon, who by the vexations of this age having gotten a temper fit for the Government, and being beſides in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with the high qualification of your glorious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, will in theſe later days bring again a golden age, for the comfort of your Subjects, and for the tranquility of the Reformed Church of Chriſt, not only in your Dominions, but alſo in theſe United Provinces, yea, and through the whole world. We hope ſo much by the Divine favour; and in that confidence we pray the King of Kings to give to your Majeſty an happy entrance into
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119407:17"/>his Kingdom, a long and healthful life, a flouriſhing and peaceable Reign, a glorious Poſterity, and after this life, the Crown of eternal life. Theſe are the Vows,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>SIR, Of your Majeſties Moſt humble, and moſt obedient Servants, The CONSISTORY.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119407:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
